hi coach Brett contas here this video is
going to discuss the differences between
the Romanian deadlift the American
deadlift the stiff-legged deadlift and
the straight-legged deadlift most people
don't know the differences between these
lists before I get started I want to
emphasize that these are just my
opinions if you talk to 10 different
strength coaches or lifters you'd
probably get 10 different answers as to
what these different lifts how they're
performed and what the differences are
but this is how I do it in my gym here
at the glute lab this these are the way
that I um distinguish the lifts from one
another so first I will start off with
the Romanian deadlift I'm going to take
the bar of the rack bar is resting
against my thigh my chest is up my
shoulders are
back watch my shins they will stay
vertical throughout the movement I sit
back the bar is skimming my legs I get
to just around just below the KNE
okay my chest is up I can't go any
further my hamstrings have reached full
the full stretch I come back up just
like
this now again notice my shins see that
see how they stay perfectly vertical all
right I'm going to keep my head and
neutral okay
so that's the Romanian
deadlift to me the only problem with the
Romanian
deadlift is that we've found here with
some of our experiments that you can do
this lift without really using the
glutes much so how do you make sure you
use the glutes in a Romanian
deadlift in this case you want to
incorporate some pelvic
motion when you use pelvic motion you
come down like this you could say you're
in a little bit of interior pelvic tilt
but probably not much as long as you
just keep a good Arch you don't want to
be you know like arched as much as
possible but you just keep a decent Arch
here you will feel the
Erectors keeping this P anti pelvic tilt
which puts the hamstrings on stretch so
from right here this is the bottom of
the American deadlift as you come up you
kind of have this hip extension combined
with posterior pelvic tilt where the
glut
are going to cause the
pelvis to roll
posteriorly and this is going to
increase glute activation
dramatically so in an American deadlift
you are going to do the same exact way
as the RDL but come up with a big glute
squeeze and you will see the bar push
forward a little bit so if you want to
come to the side um an an American
deadlift you start from here same thing
I'm going to sit back descend to just
below the kneecaps and then squeeze the
glutes so you'll see this bar path see
the bar push
forward and another thing come up close
from the
front this bar is skimming my thighs the
whole
time
so one thing you do not want to do with
the American deadlift is round the low
back you will come down you will come up
and there's a glute squeeze but there is
no lumbar motion there might be some
upper back rounding and there's some
pelvic posterior pelvic tilting with the
lumbar spine does not move you're using
the glutes to to tilt the
pelvis all right some lifters would just
say that a good
Romanian deadlift is an American
deadlift but I've never seen a coach
really emphasize the glute squeeze in an
RDL and so when you do it that way you
end up using the glutes more and um kind
of sharing the load between the glutes
and the and the hamstrings there was a
lift that was popularized by Louis
Simmons a while back with Westside
barall Club he called him dial deadlist
um which stood for Matt DL the guy who
would do them most often and they're
just High rep American
deadlifts um done for like 15 to 30 reps
so again you just come down a little bit
maybe not below the kneecaps and you
just squeeze the glutes you use about
say 20 to 40% of your one rep max dead
lless so I could use like 185 or so and
just do them High Reps just kind of like
this
and you doing right it kind of feels
like a hip thrust because you're pushing
the hips forward with the
glutes okay now moving on to the stiff
leg deadlift and the straight leg
deadlift a lot of coaches would not name
a discrepancy between these two they
would think that they are
synonymous but I don't think they are
the way at least the way that I learned
years ago to me the stiff legged
deadlift you can start the the Romanian
deadlift or the American deadlift you
want to start out of the rack so you're
starting from the top down the stiff
legged deadlift you can start start from
the top down or start from the bar on
the floor and all it is is a high hip
deadlift where you're trying to keep the
hips as high as possible while still
having a neutral sparing so if I come
down here and I'll do them double overs
if I come here this is as high as I can
get the hips without rounding my spine
so I'll just go from
here you will notice that my legs do
Bend come to the
side my legs are bending in a stiff
legged
deadlift so like
this
so see how my legs Bend all right so
that's a stiff legged
deadlift in a straight legged
deadlift I am going to actually keep my
legs straight My legs will be they're
not like locked out like this but they
will be straight I will not be bending
them now when you do the straight the
straight legged de you will sit back the
bar will actually separate from the body
this is the only lift the only variation
where the bar
doesn't you know doesn't drag against
the
thighs so the straight leg deadlift I
would normally start out of the
rack so i'
start from
here take it out of the
rack okay chest up shoulders back lock
the
legs
so really like from right here I can't
go much deeper because my legs are
locked out and I am keeping my chest up
this is about as deep as I can go if I
do go deeper watch what I end up
doing I end up rounding my
back like that you see a lot of um like
old school bodybuilders who do it that
way in fact um a lot of guys used to do
these standing on a bench press they'd
stand on the bench you know on the mat
with a very narrow stance go all the way
down until the bar touch their their
feet their
shoes I do not recommend
that uh so like it kind of go like
this
see the bar is touching my shoes right
now and they
go like that and keep the legs as
straight as possible while rounding the
spine that probably won't hurt you if
you're going
light using really light loads like 135
or
185 but uh you know you start getting
stronger at that that's probably going
to take it toall so I do not recommend
doing them that way but you could do
them the way I showed where you keep the
spine arched the bar will drift away a
little bit you do feel a good stretching
the hamstrings that way but it doesn't
work the glutes well so for that reason
we do not do the straight legged
deadlift very
often here at glute lab we don't do
Romanian deadlift because American
deadlifts are better and we do
stiff-legged dead this so let me review
those one more
time Romanian
deadlift start from the top chest up
shoulders back sit back head and neutral
come up the only difference between an
RDL and an American deadlift is the RDL
you don't come up and squeeze the glutes
with American Dead glutes squeeze bar is
push forward so American deadlift like
this
um stiff legged deadlift bars on the
ground hips are
high hips are as high as I can
go and then you have the straight legged
deadlift which start from the top lock
the
legs
again we don't really do the straight
leg deadlift we don't do the Romanian
deadlift we stick to the American Dead
and the stiff legged dead here I hope
you enjoy the video